I'm called over the regular schedule, me and my name is City Council, Monday May 15th, 2023.
We're not at number two, the proclamation declaring the first Friday in June will be National Gun Violence Awareness Day.
The proclamation was in your packet.
You know, I think we have a group of ladies here that are willing to accept this if we approve it.
That being done.
This is the most recent one I think there is a few changes from the ones in the packet.
Yes.
The only changes were the fifth whereas.
I don't even have a copy of this.
I believe that's.
So the only changes were were.
So whereas public safety in the communities they serve is the mayor in Council's highest.
Responsibility.
And whereas the mayor in City Council fully support the second amendment rights of law buying citizens.
Which goes hand in hand with keeping guns away from people with dangerous histories.
So the only changes in that line there from the ones you have in your packet.
Sing.
Williams.
He says.
Michael.
Hi.
Member.
Perfect.
All right.
I will present this.
Thank you, thank you all.
Time to go.
Yeah, every time you say something like that.
Thank you so much.
Three, both again, but let's get to the personal appearances.
We have none.
Four claims list.
We're going to send my proof.
Second.
Hi.
Five minutes from the May 1st, 2021.
Regular meetings.
Motion.
Second.
Six presentation from my area of account.
Services, Mr. Chan and do home.
Well this was about to throw something at me.
You got three minutes.
You missed.
I shall be quick.
Recently, I completed a course on real estate development.
I won't guarantee that I did not model a few times.
It was a very informative class.
There was some interesting things that came up.
I actually shared one of the screens with both because I thought it was important.
But it's always always like to remind you of our strategic initiatives.
It made business retention and expansion.
Workforce development.
Recruitment and new business collaboration.
An area you municipal county tribal governments.
The reason I'm here today.
Revenue growth.
Both for the surrounding area and my organization itself.
In marketing and branding.
That's our strategic initiatives.
Some of those will always be there.
Some of those will change.
Maybe going into 24.
the top three are our biggest focus. They're always a big part of what I do every single day.
And so we'll talk about that. But one of the things that came out of that class, and the reason I'm sharing with you
Bo and I talked about this, it's not to, it's basically to look at it from the standpoint of,
these are the top 20 things that site selectors are looking for when they're talking about finding a location
or the expansion or the start of the new business or whatever the case may be.
And so when Bo and I were talking about this, the one of these is this appeal to me is because it's kind of a checklist.
It's an opportunity for us to see kind of where we are today. It's going to show where we're strong.
And it's going to show some of those areas that aren't necessarily weaknesses, but opportunities to improve and get better.
So we'll go through it kind of quickly, but if you have a question, because I only got a couple minutes now.
If you have any questions, I'm happy to stop it, answer those questions.
But we'll breeze through this pretty quickly, but we'll do the 20 things, and then what I wanted to show you.
So keep this in mind as we move forward. You don't have to check every single box every time.
Not every company is looking for the same thing every time.
So the important thing is how many of these items can we check.
And then from that, I'm going to end looking at how we receive information,
primarily through the partner commerce, which they look for, but on proposals from companies that are looking for location and what their price area are and how we determine which of those requests we can reply to.
Because our ability to reply is going to be based on what they're asking for.
How many of those boxes we can check, things like that, that makes sense?
What can I sort of?
So the number one on the list is highway accessibility.
So when you look at my M.A. as a whole, because of higher state 44, 69A, we're actually pretty good when it comes to that.
In industrial war, the progress in industrial war, since on 69A, quick access to 44,
or if you want to go to North, in the Kansas areas, you can.
So that's in check as far as I'm concerned.
And then you talk to one of the Barbara Commerce, let's say that we do well there.
In the stock, you can see in construction costs, everybody's construction's cost right now, but through the route.
That's just across the board.
And the region you are in the country determines the extent of how high those costs are in the very, everyone else.
We're actually not that bad.
But on this one, I didn't give us a check.
I kind of gave us a side where he's not much about it.
Because it's affecting everybody.
Available land, I want you to remember number three,
that it's a single biggest challenge of my job.
It's available land.
And you'll see why I'm talking about,
when I give you those two examples from the Department of Commerce,
as a thumb down for us.
Right now, but it's also why I'm working
for reaching out to a lot of the people in this county
that have available land and try to use their property
in responding to those proposals.
Not that I'm taking anything from,
and certainly it means that in the admit
that those sites are selected,
there would have to be an exchange of money for that property.
But just to be able to use those properties
in responding to some of those LARFPs.
Available buildings.
That's a kind of a sideways thumbs.
You know, though, are down.
We don't have that many available buildings.
And more importantly, we don't have that many available buildings
that meet the new wave of requests we've been seeing lately.
This is the spec building in the industrial park.
It's 54,000 square feet.
The minimum size we're seeing now is 150,000 square feet.
And large.
So available buildings is a problem.
It doesn't mean we can't get around those.
It's just if a site selectors come in and they demand
to have a certain building already in the existence.
That means those requirements.
Then we're going to have to figure something out.
But we just don't have that many available buildings.
Available buildings is skilled labor.
Depending on what the job is,
what the company produces, when you're back through the walls.
If you had to rely on the city of Mayan,
along we're probably so, so there, you back up and you take in account
a lot of what can't even, you know, that don't start to raise a little bit.
But when you factor that most people won't have a problem these days,
you're working for five minutes or 30 minutes.
That takes them on much more to cool.
And we actually do pretty well.
And so from a skilled labor standpoint, we can compete.
Labor costs in Mayan are, what can I just region is a whole or pretty low.
I'm not saying they should be, but they are.
It's one of the issues that we're facing.
You remember that on that strategic condition,
one of those in the workforce development,
but can tell you, because he's serving all of our committees,
workforce development, current salary structures in Available can be,
or always.
We sometimes the argument in my life again, he isn't that we have a job problem, we have a wage problem.
Shannon, on the labor costly, is that with respect to Oklahoma widers, or are you talking about national?
No, that's what they're looking at labor costs, no matter where they're looking to go.
So compared to national, Oklahoma's got to look pretty good.
We look great, Oklahoma's the whole, it's really well.
In this particular region of the state of Oklahoma, it does extremely low wages.
And so that's kind of a plus and a minus, but overall it's a plus, because as we're talking with companies,
they want to know what this is going to cost them to book people over here.
And because Oklahoma's salary on wage costs are so low, we do well.
And that way is the state that in this particular part of the state.
Right to work at state. We're good there.
Propivity to major markets, another plus for my amazement is its geographic location.
When you consider we have job in Springfield, it's not that far, not West Arkansas, it's not that far, it's not that far.
And even if you extend beyond that, to Oklahoma City, from Kansas City, we're geographically, we're a pretty good location.
Energy, availability, and cost, this one I was getting to trouble, but I'm going to say it to you anyway.
The state of Oklahoma has some of the cheapest utilities in the country.
And that includes the city of Miami.
And I know that's a hot button topic issue sometimes on the page that's a shall not be named on Facebook.
But if you really sit down and you look at where Miami is from, or rates, they don't point.
I think utility costs here are not that bad.
And when you look at Oklahoma as a whole, they're fantastic.
Both sat in on the conversation I had one day with a councilman and we asked the one place.
So what is your interest in the Northeast Oklahoma?
It goes cheap, you should tell me out.
That's a reality. We may not want to get that, but it's a reality.
Corporate tax rate, tax exemption, state, local tax incentives.
Maybe they kind of all love together, but they haven't broken out separately.
There's not much we can do about the corporate tax rate here in Miami.
Tax exemptions get real tricky here in the city of Miami as well.
We don't have to history or anything like that.
So that's not an area that really applies to us.
We just don't have to be able to do that.
State, local tax incentives.
I will say that the state of Oklahoma, the Department of Commerce, has an excellent program.
incentives for companies. That's why you see so many companies looking at over
on the right now. This is the area I'm more concerned about. Right now we just
don't have a lot of local tax incentives. And by tax incentives I'm going to take
out the word tax and just say local incentives. There's not a whole lot that
cities has set up right now overnight at lots of conversations about this.
We do have some ideas. We're trying to flesh some of those out.
We get those before they cancel the nice decisions. You have, I believe,
artists discuss some options when it comes to retail.
Developing what you can do with certain new retailers that come to town.
And that's a huge step in the right direction.
But we need to take that and now think a little bit bigger.
What can we do when we're attracting industry into Ottawa County to offer
some local incentives to help. There are things that you do currently offer.
I won't go into them to hear if you want to meet with me later.
We can have that discussion. But you're already doing some things.
And most of it has to do with providing utilities to a location.
And most kind of things. You know that. You already do a lot.
But there are some other things we can do that are all the same lines that
what you're doing from a retail standpoint.
But just looking at it from a different perspective.
When the coming months and then monetary will be able to have that conversation.
It's been an expedited or fast track permitting.
That's one of the things the city is really worked on.
It's trying to be quicker and more responsive.
In responding to permits for buildings to start construction.
This is just our construction.
I think the city is doing a much better job of that.
In some areas.
There are different things applied.
Different types of businesses.
So thank you.
You look up.
It's a lot of things.
Doing a much better job.
Low Union growl.
Really not much easier here.
It comes up.
Inbound outbound shipping costs.
Do you get graphic location kind of comes into this as well.
Because we're so close to Tulsa,
Joplin, Northwest Arkansas.
I can't say Oklahoma City.
Those areas.
Our location to 69, 69,
44, the railroad, the rail spur,
and the industrial park.
All of those things help to cut down on shipping costs.
Because we come to simply look into the country.
You can pretty much get to anywhere from here.
If you go back and buy a renewable and we have a business with a sector back in February.
One of the things they talked about repeatedly about my Oklahoma is its location.
It's easy for them to get their product out from here.
They're only other options to go to Texas.
And they really didn't like that option.
Environmental regulations, we don't have that wrong here today.
You start getting into things like
Greenfield sites, grayfield sites, brownfield sites.
All of those things have certain environmental checklists
that you have to go to their Oxplain, what those are a little bit later.
But we do have issues in environmental issues.
In this particular part of the country, as a result of the lensing
mind that's in place back in the evening.
We're talking about, we really don't have a lot of options here.
Because you're talking about multi-million dollar projects,
there's a future of the industry.
We do have a few that are capable of handling the projects like that.
Most of the companies, however, are going to work that financing out before we
give some of you to our level.
There's an opportunity to say about the only people who have a financial
authority.
Other laws and venture capital firms in the country that take care of that.
I don't worry too much about 17, because I think there's two
in the other options available around.
Yeah, I'm kind of here because I think 18 and 20 to me go together.
And I think we do pretty well there.
My high school's got a real good program in place with now.
And I think we're going to have to do that.
I think we're going to have to do that.
My high school's got a real good program in place with now.
We have Northeast Career Tech, which has an excellent training programs.
And we're also very fortunate to have an artificial knowledge.
Two of the three of those were well said to develop training programs
and provide the technical training that any industry
will get to come to our locality.
And then 19 has skipped over that.
Accessibility to major airport, against geographic location.
I think that's a plus for us.
We have an airport here, but we also have an airport of job load.
There's only a road.
More importantly, there's one big one in Northeastern.
North West Arkansas.
There's a big one in Tulsa.
A little city.
He keeps a city not that far away.
I think we can check that bus.
Again, those are the top 20 things that you're looking for.
To start a new manufacturing operation somewhere.
Those are the kind of things that people look at.
And we need to make.
Which gets us to the no-clone.
A lot of apartments, which maintains the open home of development project portal.
And that portal was designed to shorten our response time for RFPs.
So business comes in.
They reach out to the state of Oklahoma, the Department of Commerce.
They say, we're a company XYZ.
This is what we're looking for.
looking for, tell me what you got.
The state of the Department of Commerce
to take that information put it into an RFP format,
in Melanaut to all of the people, all in the economic development
offices within the state.
And then it's up to you to go to respond.
I'm going to give you two examples of proposals
that came through in the last month, one in which we submitted
a response to and one in which we did,
oh, let's see if you figure out which one.
Well, let's do it.
So, example one, this project code name, AECM,
but they do all has some really crazy names
in my project line sector,
or whatever the case could be,
and they're very creative at the core.
It was doing on April 20th.
It's making factory company.
So here's some of their basic needs.
Company land project with operations
seeking to relocate to Oklahoma.
They need a minimum of 10 acres of existing building,
or the ability to be the need is for
1500 square feet of office space, 10,000 square feet of warehouse space,
50,000 square foot of production space,
with potential to expansion of 75 to 100,000 square feet.
So there's just a building dimensions again.
And the anchor is, here's the power need.
So this is something that others have to be following
with more, and say, hey, can we meet these requests?
Because if we can't even meet the power needs,
then there's not much need for us to apply.
There's a natural gas requirement.
They primarily use natural gas to produce steam,
and they're production process.
There's the water requirements, waste water requirements.
They need access to the interstate and highway,
and another option to check earlier.
There we go.
Real access, we just so happen to have a real spread
that runs right through the industrial board.
We also have a 50,000 square foot building
that could be finished to meet their building needs.
And that building sits on 11 and a half acres.
They mean 10.
And it's a great, they're looking for a green field side.
So you don't agree with what side is.
So the three major field types that you deal with
in this business, green field means that it's currently just
a few.
That doesn't mean that field doesn't have history.
And you have to research it back to see
what was ever on that location, the term that there's any other
environmental concerns that you may require,
or seem special permitting, or have to give EPA a year,
be due involved with it.
The green field side is essentially just what it sounds like.
It is essentially an open bit.
They strongly prefer to be within a foreign train zone,
but it's not required.
And the company needs real access to the board established.
that we're actually part of though.
So that's example one, example two, I call the next one, Z.
It was doing for fifth, it's a major factor in industry.
And they are looking through established or manufacturing
and distribution facility in Oklahoma.
They're from primary focus's production,
but they are currently looking for existing structure to occupy
and count growth anticipated to reach 300 by end of year
and three, that's 400 jobs by the end of year, three.
Totally investment is currently unknown.
I don't have all of your information on here,
because of confidentiality.
I keep put a lot of specific details about distributed
highlights of what we're looking for.
Here's what I said that average now,
the size we're looking for, 200 to 500,000 square,
the under roof, and spec building it.
The 25 acres, the dimensions on the ceiling height,
or spec building, we cover that.
The main interstate, major highway access,
or intake, and now taking the trucking,
they're looking for a population base of 500,000 per acre.
And so out of those two examples,
which one did we apply for first?
We could, this wasn't such a sticking point, put it in.
There's actually that much base available
when we do industrial or there.
So there's 25 acres available there,
and we can certainly build to suit for them.
But we just don't have anything that big,
you close to that big, that's currently available.
She didn't want to evaluate it.
One like that, that says population of 50,000 per acre.
How far up do you look at that about?
Would you consider us to meet that since we've got 30?
Well, we've got a lot to do, because of, again,
you take in, again, you put a dot in the center
of Miami, and you go an hour's drive within an hour's drive.
So I absolutely know.
This one's been scared me, none of this scared me except that.
And there were some other, I think, back up.
So I did put all of the power source requirements on here,
and the Tyler would probably have a stroke.
Or I said, let's build some new equipment tomorrow,
because it was pretty demanding.
It's the most I ever seen.
So I don't know.
Because that's something that...
building size, the massive size they want. I mean if they had the acreage, they
came in and built themselves.
They could.
Here's the thing.
They're looking for the existing structure.
They don't want to have to take the 50, but they're pretty straightforward.
And so, we get these regularly from the park.
First thing I got to do, I get them to go along and look at all the specs and then
determine if we have the ability.
They're minimum.
These are the minimum requirements.
So, once you get past this, then you've got to go back to the 20 top things that they're
going to be.
Some other things that they're going to want.
You just got to have to clear this hurdle first.
We made the first cut, by the way, on that first example.
Make the second cut.
Any question?
I just wanted to share that with you because those are the things I just felt like it was a good opportunity
to touch on some of the things that sites and lectures were looking for.
To give an example of how we've come across leads for opportunities to bring new industry
into our area.
A big source of that is through the Oklahoma Commerce Project.
And so, we probably get eight to ten of those types of requests every month.
And on average, we apply, we respond to some of them.
Today, any questions?
You got any good news you can share that's anything on their horizon.
Which is all look like number two.
Okay.
So, I'll try to be as around that as a best I can.
So, if I'm a politician now, I'll have a minute.
Here's our order of directors.
You'll notice two names from the last time I was here.
So, two of our longstanding board members that are present on.
We're really sure.
Jason Blubbins.
So, they are working on our project now that we'll bear some fruit for us.
And because there was a potential conflict, they felt that necessary to those are...
What do we do to pass the snow?
Pass the snow, pass the snow, pass the snow, pass the snow.
And so, they took the initiatives and they, because we want to come back and approach you about this,
we think it's only right for us to step down.
Yes.
So, we have to speak.
That's all you got.
So, you can...
If this is our board, I don't know those are chairperson breading.
last year and today, as you all know, in our board members, Nick I Smith, Dr. Stafford,
the NEO, received a manager for the Race of Arcusa, Michael Arcomcommer, Blake,
Clayton, Cameron Wilkins, and Shawn, they are our local bankers. Chief Craig Harper, and
Mike first from the County Commission, and the Government really gives you an important place.
This mod later this month, we're going to be hopefully filling some blanks there, and adding a couple
of new board, hopefully made to them. That's it. For me, I contacted information that anybody
needs it. I think it's in your back end. Before I go, I didn't want to say that, or just, I
know everyone remembers this, but so last week, we lost Mr. Virgil Jordan's mark, and we certainly
know the impact that he and his company have had on our local economy throughout the years.
He was a tremendous employer, an innovator in the ag industry, and so he certainly would be missed
in our thoughts and prayers continuing to go out to him. It's family. I do want to tell you just a real
quick story. I go back to when I first moved here, a long time ago, 2001, and I wasn't here, very long,
and we were running a half my wife and I, just the, we were running a house from Woody Painter,
but virtually when we first moved here. We had to have a fancy yard and he was the only one
of that house with a fence yard. I woke up one morning, early, I think it was a Saturday morning,
the wrap we moved into the house, and I walked outside, and I was just like, what is that? And I started
walking around my house, I started walking around my vehicles, and I can't find that smell and say my life.
I don't know what's going on. I had never smelled anything like it in my life. And I was out there
for probably 35 or 40 minutes, when my neighbor apparently was watching me the whole time, and he came out,
and he had this big grand on his face and his couple co-hosted couple coffee and he was like, what's
you doing? I said, look at him like he was crazy. I said, you don't smell that, he laughed, and he goes,
you know what that is, huh? No, so why am I all forced, you're looking under my vehicle,
it's not going to ran over something. He goes, that's a smell of money. And I said, man, I don't know your
backstory, I don't know much about you, but I'm never handled money that's really like that.
And he laughed, and then he proceeds to tell me what it really is. And I never forgot that, because it was
one of the first encounters I had in my amma, and it wasn't until many years later working at the
newspaper for as many years as I did, but I came to R-
realize that you know he was actually right but it's more than that it is a smell of money
to an extent but you know what the most important thing is and people need to remember
this it's the smell of jobs right you've got people within your own organization here
that I hear you one time or another probably worked for Jane in terms of some of that
and so it's vital to this community yeah we may have to put up with a few things to
it's not the most pleasant smell but you know what it put people to work it grew
a tremendous company and what it really is is the smell of opportunity.
Opportunity for a lot of people in this community to find employment opportunity
for a lot of people to earn a living to go on to bigger and better things
whether they stayed there for 20 years or they was their first job out of high school
or the first job that they had and they moved on to something bigger and better the
point is Virgil Jurgersmire created a company that provided jobs it's
demulated our economy if you don't know agriculture is one of it is the largest
single industry in auto-economic. Not the mushroom format itself but all ag in total those
are opportunities and it takes people like Virgil Jurgersmire to have a vision to have
a dream and to actually work hard to make that dream a reality his company is legacy to
what he did and it continues to grow and expand and we all reap the benefits of it whether we
want to realize it or not so I hope you remember that reach out to the family if you get a chance
let them know that you're thinking about them that you're thoughts and prayers or with them
but Virgil Jurgersmire was an asset to my am I it's company still is to this day thanks
for the question I don't want to take away from Virgil Jurgersmire he means that I was going to ask
before you started the loan program you talked about that just a little bit tell us how that's going
sure so if you don't know made's operates what's called a revolving loan program so back when the
organization was founded back in the mid-80s after good rich shut down the federal government gave the
organization right around $2 million to create the revolving loan fund which is to be used
to help grow the economy so if you have a business you're looking to expand if you have a business
you're looking to start it was an opportunity for folks to go and get funding to help achieve
to help reach those goals whatever those funding limits are there are some requirements to the
program you have to because the organization is not a bank even though we act like a bank sometimes
same requirements, we are not as regulated as a bank is, but we also more importantly don't
want to compete with our local financial institutions.
So, it made us set up where you go and you try to seek your funding first through the local
financial institutions.
We actually require that you have two rejection letters from a local financial institution, then
you can come back to us because banks have a very narrow focus.
They look at everything like this, we tend to take a much broader approach, we look
at the bigger picture, and we look at the need, we look at the opportunity, and we take
on or risk in the local financial institutions, so as a result, we will fund projects that
are going to carry some risk, but it's the best way to get those businesses in those industries
started.
So, we have reorganized that program, we are in the, we have a meeting this week, actually,
with a loan committee, we are reorganizing our paperwork, and we are actually working with
people now to point them in the right direction.
So, the first thing we ask is just like the bank does, do you have a business plan, do you have
your financials in order, we ask those same kind of criteria that the bank has, and if they
don't have that information yet, we tell them take a deep breath, don't panic, it's all
good, we have resources here locally that are free to you to help you pull all that information
together.
And that's a small business development center at INEO, Sandra Pierre, he's over that, and
we send her quite a few people, and going through that process, some of them have realized
they're not just not ready yet, and we have a few, Mr. Duckel sent me someone, and we're
still working with them right now, and I think we're close, so that's a prime example of
an opportunity that someone referred someone to us, we got them connected with the right
people to get their plan together, and now I think within the next couple of weeks they're
ready to come back to us and start talking about the financial order that, which, so that's
a company that's looking local company, looking expand a little bit, grow, get their own
building, and I think it's a great opportunity, he's got great ideas, he wants to really grow
and add new product lines, so hopefully we can help him be a part of that.
Good people.
But we do have funds available, so the way of revolving loan program works, Kevin Borles money
from me, that he goes out, and he makes his payments, and every time he makes a payment, all that
money goes back into the program, so when the next person comes along, I have money to loan
out.
So we survive as an organization through the support of the city of Miami, we survive it through
the support of private donations from our businesses and industry in town, and we survive
all of the interest that those loans generate.
Well I've had several people coming to me in that.
ask him not always say no one today so again it's a second or third conversation he
and I've had but it's a good resource so if anybody approaches he was put an
idea like that said in Shannon and if you know like he said if they don't have
to plan together whatever he can try to help get that set up with Sandra but it's a
good program that not everybody has correct yeah not and we're one of the few in the
state of Oklahoma actually economic development all this is that operator
we're evolving long program that is very specific it's designed to help
entrepreneurs get started the fuel that entrepreneurial spirit are it's
designed part of those business retention and expansion efforts we talked
about earlier it's designed to be part of that as well to help those companies
expand and it could be something as simple as we may not wind up being the
primary financing agency we may be with and serve a gap financing role so
in other words the banks willing to give them x amount of dollars but they have to
come up with the first fifty thousand or whatever we can provide that service so that
the bank will pick it up from that point so like the bank may say I'm only going to
give you eighty percent of what you're asking for we can come in and fill that twenty
percent so there's lots of options available in the interest rate we are we're
not a bank but we try to stay with the banks so I'm just throwing numbers these are
not today's interest rates but just as an example if the banks are at six percent
which I think they're higher than that now if they're at six percent then we're going
to be probably seven percent we're not one of those long companies that charge you like
thirty percent or forty percent interest we don't do that it's designed to help people
out and they get three minutes exactly I'm seven budget amendment number twenty three
to ask twenty two reversing and correct the amendment twenty three to fifteen they're
seeking to venture let's talk about it grant for fifteen hundred dollars it was already
budget airport and MDRA Coleman merit raise adjustment to cover over just in payroll
accounts and each important so the last few years we have come with an amendment
regarding moving money for merit raises this is the one from this year there is
also an adjustment that's huge that's been signed that goes with this also so there were a
lot of openings they can see this year so we were able to move money inside the funds and the
other one was a miscommunication on a library let's talk about it they did get more money this year
but they didn't get that much more money so we're reversing that we've already budgeted that
portion the first portion we're in budget the additional you've seen that
Make a motion we approve.
Aye.
Thanks, too.
The rate.
Ordance.
2023-25.
Amendment Section 1-5.
I'm Chair for one.
So this is the amendment that we've talked about here a couple of times.
It's just to help clarify.
Now that we have the animal ordinance in place with things that we're doing through
community development where they can issue administrative proceedings.
It's just to clarify all of that.
And if that I'd be glad to answer any questions.
We've had a couple of discussions at the work studies.
Some of the administrative fees that keep them keep you out of the court.
I mean if you have a fine or whatever.
I mean is it just an administrative deal.
The administrative.
The main advantage of the administrative proceedings is it allows other staff to be handling it rather than the police department.
It's cheaper for us to proceed that way.
We through the, for instance, the animal ordinance you set what the administrative fines would be.
Often they're very similar in reflecting what they would be if it was a criminal action handled by the police department.
But we're saving money because we're doing it through other staff than the PD.
And if I don't pay the fine once it goes to court, the judge can issue it one.
Yes.
It still allows for enforcement through the court.
This still allows animal ordinance to issue the tickets.
Well.
Okay.
So technically the administrative folks, issues, citations, the law enforcement issues, the information's or tickets.
But they can write a citation there.
Right.
And I'll keep you.
You can have it come out.
Right.
Yeah. Now some of the offenses.
For instance, a vicious dog complaint that has to be done by the PD.
They can.
initiate the process, they can get the PD out there, they can help in the investigation,
but the information has to be issued by the PD for that, particularly if it's.
The ones that we really want to have the teeth on, those are done by the police department.
The witnesses, the final graph.
This is the final graph.
And you're good with it?
That's what we're doing.
You're good?
Motion will approve.
So, five.
Five.
Eight.
Number nine is the merge cause for that's 2023, the one we're just discussing.
We're going to get in the action.
We're actually already having administrative citations issued, so we really need the blessing.
Did you do that?
Motion approved.
Yes.
Double.
Five.
Member.
You stepped up.
Five.
Ten.
Mayor's nomination to a point, Kyla Perry, to the moment downtown, redevelopment authority, MDRA,
replacing Richard O'Leard, termed to expire 8.29 or 24.
Thank you.
Number four.
Four years.
All right.
Double.
Five.
Eleven.
Got the new business of any of which the resistance is the posting of this agenda.
I had one item I wanted to bring up to the council's attention, maybe for some discussion as well.
Obviously, since this agenda was published last Thursday, the State of Pellot Court issued a ruling,
which is no surprise to us, but issued a ruling that the Miami-Pioriate in Ottawa tribes actually still exist.
Again, no surprise to us.
But with that, obviously, it does fall to the city at this point in to coordinate, and so I thought it would be good
up to maybe have things to be in bed enough to count a little bit on.
What that means to the city and what our response should be, so will it you to take it over?
So the main thing is the court did make the determination that these reservations still exist as reservations.
That's big for us because we've been in limbo for two years, three years now since McGurt decision was made.
The U.S. Attorney's Office took the position that they were not reservations, and so they refused to do what their job obligation would be if they were reservations.
Whereas our courts, the local courts, had ruled that they weren't.
still reservations and therefore it was a federal responsibility. We got we got we're the ones that got caught in no man's land
Where nobody was doing what needed to be done?
The answer is a lot of the questions. It doesn't answer all the questions, but it does
hopefully it will
for instance
cause the
feds to expedite the process of getting our officers
the certification that they need so that they are covered by a federal
hat when they're operating in the field right now. We don't have that
They have an expedited process available, but they wouldn't do it because they were saying it's not reservations
so it
It helps us significantly in many ways, but it doesn't answer all of our questions
For instance, we're still in
somewhat of a limbo situation
if we have a juvenile that is native
that commits a major crime
in our city limits
because the feds generally do not prosecute juveniles
our position would be it's a federal matter to deal with
We don't know the answer, we don't know how the U.S. attorneys office is going to handle these things
But those are few and far between
the vast majority of what's going on. We think we have answers on
I would also add that
the position that I've taken and our judge has agreed all along is that as far as
other misdemeanor offenses
we
have jurisdiction under the curse act
the federal court in Tulsa has agreed with that position
but that is on appeal to the tense circuit and we
you know they they may do something different but
that this decision doesn't affect that we still feel that we have jurisdiction in city court
for any traffic offense anything that is a misdemeanor
that may be done by a native of American
in the city limits
We can't prosecute felonies in city court so
this decision doesn't affect us as far as city court is concerned at all
but it will hopefully
get everybody on the stick so that you know we have all the troubles that we've had in the jail
um
the opinion does send it back to the district court for a little bit more fact finding
I don't think any of that is going to make a significant difference
what's going on. I have not had the opportunity to talk with Doug the District Attorney about
this since the ruling came out Friday. Actually we didn't find the written opinion until today.
So we didn't really know what the court had said until today. That's why it's just now coming up under
new business. But I think he and I are pretty much in agreement is to what all this means.
May or may not be really a good thing other than we've got some answers. That's the main thing. We've
got some answers now. And maybe we don't have to turn people loose that can go the federal right.
Like we have. Would it work to have an MOU with the tribes through the city here?
We will do whatever we need to do. At one time we had all of our city officers carrying an SLAC,
which is the federal commission that we need. That got undone over the past 20 years. I think that's
what is going to be our answer. I still have mine. Okay, but you're not a single one.
No, you need to be sorry. How long has it taken to get that certification? It's a long process,
but now that it's been determined to be a reservation, that should really speed up the process.
And I think every police officer we have, I mean we must have a real index with commission cards because
there's ever one that is going to take some of this problem. There are some of this issue by any cross commission,
but I'll try to renew, or we're involved to have one. We're going to have one. We're going to have a cross commission.
Here, there's Jeremy's cross commission, as all our officers, so we do business with more,
one more, one more, my next reservation, which is conferred in the work, both as panels,
B.I.A. covers all our tribes, and purely credit contracts with B.I.A. and now that's been stopped for a
reservation, the purely side is kind of, that's another issue there. From third avenue to the river,
we're a church, we've picked out this all of a tribe, since they brought the Canadian contract with B.I.A.
That's probably the idea, so we'd see the take with us there. So, many of them may have offended there, but we'll have to be able to take care of that.
With reports, like that, we hold the B.A.A.A.A.
while they're working 12 artists, and I don't know they thought, because they just, they're following the
terrible leads. We're going to never today, last year, B.I.A. to bring it on.
and we're going to take all of our members to point for about.
So, there's a bunch of different things going on.
And we're going to help them.
And we've been reports, and thank you for coming to that.
We're asked to make their report.
We'll do it.
All right.
Still, I've been sitting here for a week to take care of.
And also, this is a good thing now.
We're going to order a limbo.
We've been following Texas.
There'll be our current retention network.
We'll take your viewers to go and bring them out.
Because we'll be able to wear a cross-tune or a cross-tune.
So now we have a clear-death based on that.
And I think that you've heard that better from here.
That I was in the conclusion to work out.
But we've started that framework.
We're working on that.
We have great partnership with all of our community partners.
We're working forward to resolve all the things.
We're going to have been better for a community now.
And now all your jurisdiction has been ruled on, right?
Yes.
And in view of the justice that wrote this opinion,
that the opinion could have been a whole lot worse.
So we're actually, at least I'm actually pretty pleased
with the opinion as it is written.
We're going to talk about time.
Long past date.
So 12 staff reports.
13 mayor council announcements.
There I got a few.
Let me take that by.
First of all, I want to remind everybody.
It's probably your email as well.
But Robert writes for retirement party.
It's Thursday.
And the South Station from 10 to noon.
It's been here 28 years.
I'm not sure exactly how many of that's our farm cheap.
But he is retiring.
So if can we all go to that muscle?
Still?
Okay.
So begin in your town.
Trust out by there if you can.
We're going to talk about Brian Baker.
Local business man.
And let's do the new records.
Caught a new state record.
118 pound.
Big head car.
It's making national news now.
That's hitting everywhere.
And of course, Brian's just Brian.
So he I'm sure he's an interesting interview for some of those guys.
But it's really helping our water system as well.
Getting things out there.
And he's killing him.
I mean, I think he's catching like seven of that.
And he thinks.
But they're huge.
But the city council cleaned up.
Remember that.
We decided on May the 20th would be this Kevin Saturday
So if you can get with Melinda and tell her what their year you want to do where you want to meet that for your area
Then she can get that without people so we can get that down and if you wanted to do our three hour or wherever you want to do
It's fine, I mean
Isn't that to be a set time or anything like that so I'll be on the 20th if anybody must come out and help. I'm sure by who would
Tyler
You do that you limited one and see you get up to lunch. Just clean up sunset
The last thing I have is the splash pad area
Kevin his guys that really busted their tails down there and that thing looks great
You know for the last weekend
It's been full about it every day since of it that I've been writing
And I want to read a message I got from a citizen about splash
And she said I draw a draw by the splash pad yesterday and notice a young girl in a wheelchair using this wing
Made my eyes filled with tears
Keep up the hard work
Keep loving on my Emma the growth and change is wonderful. I felt so proud to be from this town that very moment
I know all too well that once small gesture like that swing
Can mean to a family that faces different challenges from day to day
proud of all of you and
That would end go to us that goes to you and your crew
I appreciate what they do
I know they don't always get the acknowledgement and praise they they deserve for what they do
But they do a good job keeping our parks in line and keeping them where our park citizens can go and use those with their kids and I'm excited to see
What the vision for that part ends up being that knows there's a vision there a lot of other people don't see yet
I know you have in your mind. I have in mind
Are my arms may be a little different but I think there's still gonna be wonderful for for the community when that park's completed
So do you know when the outdoor fashion can open up
And it looks good both are a bit down that slide and then slide and get hurt
But but great job, but you guys and I just want to read that note everybody because that was pretty special because you don't get a lot of the good
You must get the bad, but that was a good one. I want to read, so
That's all I have so
14 city magic communication
Well, absolutely want to pile on the comments to Kevin to his crew. It's been amazing watching that
Transformation out there and and also taking my little granddaughter's out there. They just absolutely love that place
They're just two and three
They enjoy that part
have lots of things they can do and play on and the big new pirate ship and the swings out there
from little ones is amazing. So it is a huge asset to this entire community having that out there.
Beyond that, I do want to share with the council a couple of challenges that we need to be aware of
and we trying to overcome. Kevin's got some significant staffing problems with our pool right now.
As you know, we normally would open up around Memorial Day weekend and so that's our goal
but that's two weeks from now. So far he's got 10 applications and he needs 18 to staff and it takes two
weeks to get those folks trained up. That's just for lifeguard. She also needs 11 members to run to
concession and we've got three applications for that. Somebody signed it up for lifeguard.
No, but I said that those ten people got a great shot.
Those ten people have a great shot. I don't know what do we live going but yeah, so we've got some challenges
there, no doubt about it. So what happens if you only have ten? We will. We have ten stations,
slide first stations. We'll open any slides or anything now. We can run it within the pool and stuff.
But the odds of having ten people show up every day, six days away, so probably nobody just does it change.
We've got to get some hockey. We've got to get through the wreck. We had a lot of applications initially.
This gets up. You guys may have already done this but if you don't mind it to put something out.
And even during this RPG program, we have a whole. So yeah.
In that, the MSRP starts June 5th. Yeah, so again. Time's running out. We've got to get some applicants in here.
I'll throw this idea out there and I'm not sure who the right person would be for this but have we thought about
reeks not to happen schools, family and schools, commerce schools, golf schools, to see if they have some
kids that may want to come over and work. We have to have a lot of them everywhere.
Cheers.
Bless some broms going to volunteer
You have to be free for them
Whisk his there's only like two life cards
You say you don't matter
If you if you draft that meant you were well if you could swim to the island and back
Yeah, jump off the high dive. You were good
I get water to the island back for they let you get
Kids page and want to do it or rather talk to my kids in Garce. She always knows people
Yeah
Something to keep you the back of your mind, you know, we've talked to the kids at Garce about combining with her the MSRP program
And we're still trying to figure out how we can make that work financially
But I think that truly for for this very reason for competing against each other
So I think we're going to have to continue to work with the kids
It may not be this summer, but I think we need to have something figured out maybe for a long-term solution to combine an efforts
She does an amazing
MSRP is free them right
And programs now
Unless we subsidized so if we took money that we're using that we're collecting and paying very most our
Pea program if we took that money and paid the kidsy
But her about the success of her problem is her program doesn't match ours because ours is only this long-cursious this long in last all day
So it's a little more expensive than what we could do
But I'm telling you guys the impact or workforce in this community to have that all day
Program like that could absolutely pay dividends
We need to she and I talked about that long time today
So we're all we're all in it together. We're all going to figure out some possible solutions, but it's just
But actually competing against each other doesn't work here
So when you make the determination if you are going to push back the opening date
So you're saying the 26
15. This means we're not being continued from Council Chambers,
right to be in the staff room, the purpose of the executive set.